<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves out of York-shire: or, an account of a iovrney, in the true discovery of a soueraigne minerall, medicinall water, in the West-Riding of Yorke-shire, neere an ancient towne called Knaresbrough, not inferiour to the spa in Germany Also a taste of other minerall waters of seuerall natures adioyning. By M.S.</title>
            <author>Stanhope, Michael.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68781</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100969</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836796</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1083</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68781)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1083)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1188:26, 1009:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves out of York-shire: or, an account of a iovrney, in the true discovery of a soueraigne minerall, medicinall water, in the West-Riding of Yorke-shire, neere an ancient towne called Knaresbrough, not inferiour to the spa in Germany Also a taste of other minerall waters of seuerall natures adioyning. By M.S.</title>
                  <author>Stanhope, Michael.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. H[aviland] for George Gibbes, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>M.S. = Michael Stanhope.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 23227.</note>
                  <note>Appears as STC 23227 (British Library copy) and STC 23228 (Bodleian Library copy) on UMI microfilm reels 1009 and 1188.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1009 (British Library copy), and at reel 1188 (Bodleian Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mineral waters --  Knaresborough --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1083:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1083:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Newes out of York-Shire: OR, AN ACCOUVNT OF A IOVRNEY, IN THE TRVE DISCOVERY OF a ſoueraigne Minerall, Medicinall Water, in the Weſt-Riding of <hi>Yorke-ſhire,</hi> neere an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Towne called <hi>Knaresbrough,</hi> not inferiour to the <hi>Spa</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo a taſte of other Minerall Waters of ſeuerall natures adioyning.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>M. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLESIAST. 38.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord hath created Medicines out of the Earth: and he that is wiſe will not deſpiſe them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. H.</hi> for <hi>George Gibbes,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Popes-head</hi> Alley. 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1083:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1083:2"/>
            <head>TO TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE vertuous, and religious Lady, the Lady <hi>Katherine Stanhope,</hi> wife to the Lord <hi>Philip Stanhope,</hi> Baron of <hi>Shelford.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſhort enſuing Diſcourſe (begotten and brought forth in the ſilent houres of a ſolitary retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) I intended at firſt for the vſe of ſome priuate friends, whom I deſired to ſatisfie in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular diſcouery of an Engliſh <hi>Spa</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. It pleaſed ſome of them vpon view
<pb facs="tcp:1083:3"/> hereof to moue me to publiſh it, for that in the whole paſſage, I perſonate my ſelfe an eye-witneſſe of all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; which they perſwaded me would giue a better gloſſe vnto the ſubiect, than any here-ſay relation. A diffidence of whatſoeuer paſſeth my pen, caus'd me a while ſuſpend my reſolution; when ſuddenly my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thoughts reflected vpon your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and then in an inſtant I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended a faire Sun-ſhine of occaſion, to publiſh vnto the world my vowed reſpects.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the vnlimited variety of your Ladiſhips rare endowments, I haue obſerued your ſpacious vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to reach, not onely to a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular meaſure of the diuine Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the ſoules ſauing knowledge (your obſeruable practiſe ſimpathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
<pb facs="tcp:1083:3"/> with the Theory) but with an extraordinary curioſity to ſearch into the Cabinets of Natures choiſeſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, eſpecially thoſe which concerne Medicinall and Phyſicall vſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your ſuccesfull hand hath vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to adminiſter in time of need with bleſt euent. Hence is it that I haue preſumed (not omitting the tie of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny noble refreſhments, and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fauours) to appropriate this ſubiect (which preſenteth vnto the world one of Natures choiſeſt Iewels) vnto your Honour; vnder the Sanctuary of whoſe vertuous protection, I am bold to promiſe to my ſelfe inuiolable ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from the rage of all ſnarling detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. It may be, your noble Lord (to whoſe immerited ſupport of my weak fortunes I ſhall euer owe a gratefull memory) might expect the addreſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:1083:4"/> my firſt fruits vnto his Honour, but I purpoſely reſerue my ſelfe till a more ample occaſion be preſented, wherein my paines may be more enlarged.</p>
            <p>I haue no greater hope to animate my aſſurance of a gracious acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than the pleaſing remembrance of your fauourable eie formerly caſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome dawnings of my weake en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoures. Faile I not herein, I haue arriued (next vnto the publike good) at the wiſh't Ports of my deſires, which as they haue euer prized, ſo ſhall they continue reſtleſſe in the purſuit of your Ladiſhips allowable eſteemes, neuer to be ſufficiently valued by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humble ſeruant, <hi>M. ST.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1083:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T what time this relation of our Engliſh <hi>Spa</hi> was (though curſorily) compoſed, the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Newes out of Yorke-ſhire</hi> (which like a Signe I fixed at the Portall of the diſcourſe) was not improper. That many Moneths are paſt, ſince it was capable of the Character of the Preſſe, and ready dreſt to encounter the publike view, it ſhall ſuffice there are diuers can witneſſe, with the caſualty of its protraction. There are (I confeſſe) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by-circumſtances enterlaced, which though they aime at lapſed time, yet are they not altogether miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliable to the preſent. In ſubſtance I differ not much from the <hi>Spadacrene</hi> lately publiſhed by a graue Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, the garbe onely of my particulariſing I challenge as mine. As for ſuch pedanticke Formaliſts, who hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may tax mee for digreſsing from the propoſed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,
<pb facs="tcp:1083:5"/> let ſuch know I hold it the greateſt ſlauery in the world to be tied to their vnneceſſary rules. But for thee (gentle Reader) be but pleaſed to obſerue the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the liberty I take, and then I hope (the dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the times conſidered, which had need of a laſh to be rowzed) thou wilt not think I roaue very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently. Yet before I leaue thee, I muſt craue thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience (as one tendering the common good) whileſt I offer to thy conſideration ſome cautions in the vſe of theſe Waters, which (if I miſtake not) are of ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all conſequence, that neglected, their expected effects are made fruſtrate.</p>
            <p>That the worth and excellency of Phyſicall helpes conſiſteth not in the remedies themſelues (as one well obſerueth) but in their wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent diſpenſation, is ſo vndoubted a poſition, as none but ſuch as ſcorne the clew of reaſon ſhould guide their vnderſtanding in the Labyrinth of ſo many vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties as are abroach in the world, will deny. And hence it is, that Medicines iudiciouſly diſpenſed, are ſaid to be as Angels of God ſent for the good of men; but inconſiderately vſed, they are Meſſengers of death. Yet ſuch is the giddy precipitation of many, eſpecially the meaner ſort of people, that they no ſooner heare of a ſecret, (be it a medicinall Water, or what elſe that promiſeth health) but (all fit circumſtances ſet apart)
<pb facs="tcp:1083:5"/> they violently ruſh vpon it, perſwading themſelues (out of a paſsionate deſire to be refreſhed) a ſudden laying hold vpon any nouelty, to be the moſt aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious courſe. Nay, how many are there who vpon notice of a new-found medicinall Spring like this of ours, queſtion not the infallibility of its curing all manner of diſeaſes? the ſottiſhneſſe of which fancy is ſo groſſe, that I will not doe it the grace of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p>Nor are the vulgar onely bleared with this miſty conceit, for I haue heard of our Empericall hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts (who take a pride (as one ſaith) to Monopolize cures vnto the prerogatiue of one Secret) who haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouched it as a thing feaſable, to compoſe a medicine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to cure any diſturbance incident to Nature. But I leaue theſe with their quaint cratchets to themſelues, and worſe company I know not how to wiſh them; and come to the obſeruances I deſire may duely be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of ſuch as intend the vſe of this our Water. And firſt I wiſh, that whoſoeuer the parties be, before they attempt the vſe of the water, they repaire to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Phyſitian, eſpecially ſuch as haue been conuerſant in the vſe and quality of the water, and make knowne to him their diſtemper, that ſo conſideration may be had of the aptneſſe of the waters faculty, how it ſtands
<pb facs="tcp:1083:6"/> qualified to the affected part, which is of ſuch condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſequele, that the omitting hereof hath proued fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall to many. For who but the Phyſitian (whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion it is) is fit to iudge of the multitude of cauſes in diſeaſes, what varying differences ariſe in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, quality, quantity, and times of remedies? wherein the party either ignorant, or miſtaken, medicines of ſauing and curing power, out of time and place diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, bring forth miſchiefe, and many inconueniences inſtead of helpe.</p>
            <p>It being granted then in the firſt place that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is of probable vſe, in the next ſucceeds a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of body, according to the nature, quality, and ſeate (as I may ſay) of each humor, which obſeruance how much it auaileth, let the common experience of thoſe, who ſubmit themſelues to aduiſe, teſtifie in the difference of the effects found from irregulars. For the manner of vſing the Water, there is no queſtion but a ſudden glutting of the ſtomake, with a ſurcharge of any thing, wherewith Nature is not acquainted, is a moſt prepoſterous courſe; yet that this is ordinary alſo (eſpecially amongst the vulgar) who knowes not, that hath obſerued the preſsing of people to theſe like waters? Soft fire (ſaith the old prouerbe) makes ſweet Malt, and a gentle acquainting of Nature by degrees
<pb facs="tcp:1083:6"/> with any thing makes it more gratefull, and ſteales as it were a kinde of familiarity with Nature. The time of the yeare by the obſeruance of the learned as moſt proper, is thought to be <hi>Iune, Iuly,</hi> and <hi>Auguſt,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, the morning beſt allowed for the circumſtance of the day. Ordinary repaſts, and the liberty at other times taken of eating and drinking, would now be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, for three or foure houres ſpace after the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the water, that ſo Nature may finiſh her taske with more eaſe, hauing the water onely for a ſubiect to grapple withall.</p>
            <p>A temperate diet by abſtaining from meates of groſſe and melancholicke ſubſtance, muſt take place as a rule amongſt the reſt worthy of remembrance, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto as a fit companion moderate exerciſe would be ioyned. Nor let ſuch thinke (whoſe bodies eſpecially are the ſeats of radicated ancient diſeaſes) to finde eaſe ſuddenly by the vſe of theſe watters; ſuch muſt come armed with a well-grounded patience, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect by degrees a leſſening of their maladies, who though haply they haue ſtaied the ordinary preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed time of the waters vſe, and yet are not ſenſible of any great change, yet let them not deſpaire, for that a ſecond yeres, triall may bring forth an happy iſſue of their deſires, whereunto this had onely the power to
<pb facs="tcp:1083:7"/> make the way. And (which is ſtrange) it hath beene obſerued, that ſome who haue by graue aduiſe beene induced to drinke of theſe waters, and haue not in any fit circumſtance digreſſed from the Phyſitians rule, though during the time of their abode at the place, they haue not perceiued any apparant amendment, yet after their departure haue beene reſtored to perfect health. The reaſon hereof the learned giue to be, that (after the drinking of the Water) there remaineth in the more ſollide parts of the body (by which the water did paſſe) the hidden faculties and powers thereof, which commonly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the effects within the ſpace of <hi>40.</hi> dayes. This hath beene obſerued as a thing of frequent experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>I had not embarked my ſelfe into theſe cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onarie aduertiſements at all, (knowing they are more punctually ſet downe by others, eſpecially in the late <hi>Spadacrene</hi>) but that at my being this Summer at our new <hi>Spa,</hi> I did obſerue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers to take a moſt prepoſterous courſe in drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Water. Some came thither, rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting a Miracle than a cure; hauing beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately diſeaſed for many yeares, and yet concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued hope of a perfect recouerie by two or three
<pb facs="tcp:1083:7"/> dayes ſtay. Others at the firſt approach to the water ſticke not to drinke (beſides the omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of preparation) as large a quantity as would require (by due order) the riſing to of ten or twelue daies, and it may be within an houre forbeare not to pleaſe the pallate with any ordinary refection. Hence (omitting a world of other errours) comes theſe waters (which in themſelues methodically vſed are of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent effects) to be ſo much diſparaged, their worth traduced, and their admirall operations obſcured by the brutiſh precipitation of moſt that haue recourſe to them; whereof if others warned will not take heed, let the failing of their deſire in the cure, nay perhaps the diſeaſe made more deſperate, or extraordinary ſymptomes hapning, be the iuſt reward and guerdon of their wilfull vnaduiſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>I am loth to leaue thee before (for thy encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement) I adde an experiment or two which (amongst others) this Summer <hi>1626.</hi> brought forth at this our new <hi>Spa.</hi> A man about the age of <hi>50.</hi> yeres (being of an extraordinary bulke of body, but eſpecially his belly of an vnſeene great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) who partly by the ſurcharge of that great
<pb facs="tcp:1083:8"/> maſſe of fleſh he carried, and partly through a ſtoppage of the paſſages of reſpiration, could not of twenty yeares before goe many paces without a pauſe, and the benefit of a ſeate, hauing drunke of this Water orderly about a fortnight, his belly did fall to a competent ſize, and hee was able to goe from the Towne of <hi>Knaresbrough</hi> to the fountain (which is little leſſe than two miles) and moſt of it vp the hill) without any deſire of reſt, or eaſing. I alſo ſaw a Youth, and ſpake with him, about the age of twentie yeares who for the ſpace of three yeares before had been miſerably afflicted with a kinde of Epilepſie, yet differing from the ordinary manner of that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, in ſome ſtrange and violent diſtortions which for the moſt part affected his right ſide. It was ordinary for him to fall three or foure times in a day, in which fits he lay groueling vpon the ground, a miſerable ſpectacle. This poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had continued the vſe of the water not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue ten dayes, during which time hee had but two fits, and thoſe exceedingly moderated. A ſtrange alteration, and not eaſily admitting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, and ſhewes that this Water is of an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble compoſure, and tranſcendent faculties, and
<pb facs="tcp:1083:8"/> worthy the curious indagation of the learned. I hold my ſelfe much to blame, that I did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire their names, and abode, for the more full ſatisfaction of thoſe who are of nice beleefe. It remaines, that of what is paſt, and doth follow, if thy obſeruance procure thee any benefit, that thou bleſſe the Fountaine of all fountains, from whom all Creatures deriue both being, and whatſoeuer is in them of worth and efficacy.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. St.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1083:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1083:9"/>
            <head>NEWES OVT OF YORKE-SHIRE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two Treatiſes, the one written by <hi>Philip Ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinx</hi> a German Doctor, the other by Mounſieur <hi>Pigrag,</hi> Chirurgian to <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Third of <hi>France,</hi> which doe ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the qualities both manifeſt and ſpecifique of the <hi>Spa</hi> water in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> the order of vſing it, and for what diſeaſes it is proper. What credit it hath gained in moſt parts of Chriſtendome, the great confluence thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all conditions of people doth make good. How many perſonages of great qualitie of this our Kingdome, haue made their repaire thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is alſo obuious to the vnderſtanding of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. But as it is to be feared, that ſome from amongſt vs haue pretended the vſe of that water,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1083:10"/> the better to colour other intentions not very allowable: (the place affording all wiſhed means of priuate conuerſe with Prieſts, Ieſuites, &amp;c.) So it may be ſuſpected (ſuch is our noted folly) that had we as effectuall a bleſſing in this land, wee would be gadding abroad through a vaine eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of whatſoeuer is forraigne. <hi>Nahaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> being aduiſed by the Prophet to waſh in <hi>Iordan,</hi> diſdainfully replyed, Are not <hi>Abana</hi> and <hi>Pharpar</hi> Riuers of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> better than all the waters of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Such are we, to whom though God hath pointed out waters of health amongſt our ſelues, yet we will not be perſwaded but <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hox</hi> and <hi>Sauanir</hi> (the two Fountaines of the <hi>Spa</hi>) doe exceed all the Springs in <hi>England.</hi> But as hee being better aduiſed, vpon repaire to <hi>Iordan,</hi> was reſtored to health, ſo there is no doubt, but if we will make vſe of our owne waters, and other bleſſings at home, we ſhall haue little need to craue the aide of any forraine ſoile. What ſo much in requeſt as the <hi>Indian</hi> Drugs, and Spice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the <hi>Ilands,</hi> procured by ſo many hazardous and tedious voiages; the opinion whereof hath ſo beſotted vs, that compared with them, we vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and diſeſteeme what our owne Nation doth afford, as if Nature had forgot to ſuppeditate this our famous Ile with neceſſaries, either for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1083:10"/> of our well being, or for the rectifying of any bodily decay, or peccant humour? Yet hath Doctor <hi>Bright</hi> (that learned Phyſitian) proued in a Tract (called the Practiſe of home Medicines) that our owne Countrey is of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient competencie, to ſupply vs with all vſefull Commodities, either for Dyet, or Phiſicke, paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelling our ordinary natiue Simples, with the choiceſt drugs, and fartheſt fetcht Spiceries.</p>
            <p>To come a little neerer to our purpoſe. It is (as I am credibly enformed) about 50 yeres ſince firſt notice was taken of a Spring (in the Weſt-riding of Yorke-ſhire, neere a Towne called <hi>Knares<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi>) called at this day by the countrey people, <hi>Tuit-well,</hi> it ſeemes for no other cauſe, but that thoſe birdes (being our greene Plouer) doe vſually haunt the place. Of this Spring (I haue heard) two neighbouring Gentlemen of ancient deſcent, the one <hi>Slingesbey,</hi> the other <hi>Inglebey,</hi> did for many yeares ordinarily drinke, for that it was ſuppoſed, as in taſte, ſo in effect, it did agree with the <hi>Spa</hi> in <hi>Germanie.</hi> I doubt not but their long continuance of the vſe of it, did proceed from a ſenſible effect found in their embettering: Nor doe I doubt alſo that they were ſparing worthily to report of it: yet (ſuch is our Lady-like humor, that we prize nothing but what is farre-fetcht,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1083:11"/> and deare bought) I cannot perceiue it gained any great credite, but hath ſince their deceaſe been altogether inuolued in ſilence, and for no other cauſe (as I conceiue) but that it is within the girdle of our owne Kingdome. Thus hath it happened that partly (as I ſaid before) through a capritious affectation of forraine traſh, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through a drowſie humour that doth inuellope vs, not endeuouring to ſearch into the riches, and opulentie, which Nature (farre from ſparingly) hath crowned vs withall; this, <hi>Tuit-well</hi> (I feare the pooreneſſe of the name, hath not a little diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduantag'd it) hath beene moſt groſly negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as if it were a place onely worth the notice of that ſilly bird.</p>
            <p>It is about two yeares ſince I firſt heard of it, at what time not meeting with any that could punctually enforme me of it, I let it paſſe as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie, yet ſo as I found in my ſelfe a kinde of itching deſire of viſiting the place.</p>
            <p>In the latter end of the Summer 1625. being caſually with Doctor <hi>Deane</hi> (a Phiſitian of good repute at his houſe at Yorke, one who is far from the ſtraine of many of his profeſſion, who are ſo chained in their opinions to their Apothecary ſhops, that they renounce the taking notice of any vertue not confined within that circuit) hee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1083:11"/> tooke occaſion to make a motion to me (the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that he remembred I had been at the <hi>Spa</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi>) of taking the aire, and to make our rendez-vous at <hi>Knaresbrough,</hi> to the end wee might be the better opportuned, to take a view of the <hi>Tuit-well,</hi> (whereof he had ſparingly heard) for that it was by ſome compared to the ſo much fam'd <hi>Spa</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I was not nice to giue way to the ſummons of his deſire; the match was ſoone made, and the next day, accompanied with a worthy Knight a iudicious admirer, and curious ſpeculator of rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; three other Phiſitians of allowable know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) we ſet forwards for <hi>Knaresbrough,</hi> being about fourteene miles from <hi>Yorke.</hi> Wee made no ſtay at the towne, but ſo ſoone as we could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided of a guide, wee made towards the Well, which we found almoſt two miles from the Towne. It is ſcituate vpon a rude barren Moore, the way to it in a manner a continuall aſcent. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our firſt approach to the Spring, we were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied that former times had taken notice of it, by reaſon it was encloaſed with ſtone, and paued at the bottome, but withall we plainly perceiued that it had beene long forgotten, which the filth wherewith it was choaked did witneſſe, beſides that through neglect the currents of other waters
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1083:12"/> were ſuffered to ſteale into it. Before any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory triall was made of it, it was thought fit firſt to clenſe the Well, and to ſtop the paſſage of any other waters intermixture, which within the compaſſe of an houre we effected. The bottome now cleared, we plainely deſcried where the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter did ſpring vp, and then the Phyſitians began to try their experiments. But firſt I dranke of it, and finding it to haue a perfect <hi>Spa</hi> reliſh, (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) I could not containe, but in a tone lowder than ordinary, I bade them welcome to the <hi>Spa.</hi> Preſently they all tooke eſſaies of it, and though they could not denie, but that it had a different ſmack from all other common waters, moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing that it did leaue in the pallate a kinde of acideneſſe, yet the better to be aſſured whether it did partake with Vitrioll the prime ingredient in the natural <hi>Spa,</hi> they mixed in a glaſſe the powder of Galls with the water, knowing by experience, if this Minerall had any acquaintance with the Spring, the powder would diſcolour the water, and turne it to a Claret die: wherein they were not deceiued, for preſently (to their both wonder and ioy) the water changed colour, and ſeemed to bluſh in behalfe of the Countrey, who had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them ſo great a Iewell and made no rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning of it. Thus pleaſed (hauing euery one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1083:12"/> taken a draught, or two) wee returned to the Towne, yet not the ſame way we came, for our guide directed vs another way, being a mile fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vp into the Moore, to ſee another Spring, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it a ſtincking Epithite, (as indeed it did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue) whereof, and of others, all bordering with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a ſmall compaſſe, I will hereafter giue a taſte.</p>
            <p>You may ſuppoſe (being met together at our Inne, where wee found our ſelues very well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated for our prouiſion) we could finde no other talke but of this our new <hi>Spa,</hi> the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors (as occaſion ſerued) reaſoning among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, of the nature of Mineralls, and of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of this waters excellency, and now and then would aske me, whether I did ſeriouſly ſpeak when I gaue my verdict for a <hi>Spa</hi> taſte: Which I confidently auerring, we reſolued the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (if the day proued cleare) to giue the Spring a ſecond viſit by way of farewell for that yeare, <hi>Michaelmas</hi> being now at hand, a time very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apt to giue a peremptory iudgement of theſe kind of waters.</p>
            <p>The next morning we were awaked with the glad tidings of a bright skie, (<hi>Apollo</hi> with his cheerefull aſpect ſeeming to ſmile vpon our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe) which oportunity was ſo welcome to vs, that we were no ſooner out of bed but were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1083:13"/> ready, and no ſooner ready but on horſebacke. Vpon our reuiſit of the Spring, vvee found it (being by our former daies care diſcharged of all incombrance) very cleare, and about three quarter of a yard deepe of vvater. The taſte of the water was growne more liuely and briske than it was the day before, and much more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible in its acideneſſe. Once more we mixed the powder of Galls with the water, which made ſuch haſte to ſatisfie vs by a rubicund colour, that now we were ready to colour too for ſhame, that we had not truſted nature vpon her firſt word. There remained now no ſcruple of the waters quality, ſo that we began freely to take our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings draughts, which wee doubled and redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, for there were of vs who drunke 15. glaſſes, and who tooke leaſt had eight or nine.</p>
            <p>After a compaſſe taken in viſiting a Spring in <hi>Bilton</hi> Parke, as alſo another called <hi>Pigeon</hi> Spring, wee came at a ſeaſonable houre to our dinner, which wee found attending vs in a plaine, but plentifull forme. I may not forget to tell how that about an houre after that we had drunke of the water, it came ſo freely from vs, that (me thought) we were like ſo many walking Conduits, ſo that for the ſpace of two houres, ſcarce a minute paſt, but ſome of vs were ready to vie it, which was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1083:13"/> preſently ſeene, and reuied by a third. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to our dinner (which for my part I had ſuch a deſire to be grapling withall, that I thought the very ſitting downe too long a parentheſis) it will not be denied but the ſight of our meat was a very pleaſing proſpect to vs all, ſo that in a few words (for we were not able to hold out a long Grace) we thank't God for a great deale of good meat. Wee were all friends, and yet who ſo had ſeene vs all ſuddenly draw at once, could not but ſuppoſe a quarrell. But (God knowes) the limits of our mallice extended onely to a ſort of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate diſhes, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> preſently yeelded to our mercy, or rather furie, for within a ſmall ſpace we had ſo pittileſly mangled them, that it was not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to know any of them by their former face. In briefe, wee all plaied the men; and had this water no other effect than this vnexpected experiment, of ſetting ſo ſharpe an edge vpon the ſtomacke, it were not to be diſreputed. It put me in minde of my being at the <hi>Spa,</hi> where though we had plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all manner of prouiſion, yet (I profeſſe) I did ſeldome riſe from table but with a crauing appetite.</p>
            <p>According to our entendment wee returned that night to <hi>Yorke,</hi> whither wee came in good time, not any of vs repenting, but rather reſulting
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1083:14"/> in our beſtowed labour. The nouelty of this diſcouery (for though it had beene formerly known, yet the memory thereof was in a manner loſt) was ſo pleaſing to vs, that we were not meal-mouth'd to trumpet in moſt places where wee came this our aduenture, as if it had beene an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Deane</hi> (whoſe thirſt of knowledge is not ſuperficially to be ſatisfied) about three daies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our returne (by the conſent of the reſt of his fellow Phiſitians) ſent for a great quantity of the <hi>Tuit-well</hi> water in large violl Glaſſes, entending partly by euaporation, and partly by ſome other Chimicall way to experiment it. Vpon returne of the meſſenger, opening a bottle to raſte it, he found it laſtleſſe; he then aſſaid to try it againe with the powder, but it denied to performe what former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it had done, as if it skorned to ſhew its Maieſty out of its owne proper throne. And had it not reaſon (thinke you) to looke pale for anger, in deſpight of Art, to be thus brought priſoner to ſo vnworthy Neighbours, who durſt neuer at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to looke it in the face but vpon ſo great an aduantage? This accident did not a little a mate the good Doctor, fearing there would lie an aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon vs all, by reaſon of our former report. But after he had recollected himſelfe, he (willing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1083:14"/> to vindicated it from all detraction) did (like a good Bee) draw from this alteration a firme and vndeniable concluſion of its worth and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to the confounding of all ſuch virulent Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as would make it a proofe of pouerty and worthleſneſſe: To wit, that ſince it is the ſpirits which giues theſe waters life, and that at his being at the Fountaine it ſelfe, the taſte was apparant, &amp; the conclusion tried with the Galls formerly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, this change did manifeſtly demonſtrate, that the water is repleate with nimble, aiery, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſpirits, which will endure little or no tranſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but by their ſubtilty ſteale away, and ſo leaue the water inſipid, and in a manner voyd of the taſte it retaineth in its naturall ſeate. This (though a truth) is ſo farre from ſatisfying ſome (if there be any truth in experience) that tell them of the inter mixture of ſpirits with the water, you may as well perſwade them it is full of Hobgob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins. But it matters not for the vulgar, who had rather ſpend their penny in good Ale, than goe from the ſmoake of their Chimneyes, to ſee neuer ſo great a wonderment of Nature, which doth preſent vnto their ſenſes (which like brutes they take care onely to pleaſe) and that ſuddenly, ſome flaſh of aſtoniſhment. Such as are of more eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpirits, who moue in a Spheare aboue the rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1083:15"/> whoſe bleſt mindes are ſed with intellectuall raptures, will eaſily admit of the probability of this change. I might adde hereunto a careleſnes in the Meſſenger, who was ſent for the water, who if he did neglect the carefull ſtopping of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, this alone were ſufficient to cauſe a maine dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. For if in liquors of a more terrene, and groſſe compoſure, as wine, let the bottle wherein it is kept, be altogether vnſtopt, or but looſely, it much abates in one night of its generouſneſſe; much more this water, whoſe brauery, viuacity, and onely faculty conſiſts in the ſpirits.</p>
            <p>Thus farre was proceeded that Summer 1625. the Doctors entending (the prime time of the yeere being <hi>Iune, Iuly,</hi> and <hi>Auguſt</hi> ouerſlipt) the following Summer, at a more apt ſeaſon to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all fit circumſtances belonging to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when the Sunne by his vigor ſhall haue clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the aire, and by vertue of his comfortable beames, and enlifening raies, giueth the height of ſplendor to all ſublunary creatures.</p>
            <p>I haue more largely than I entended diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the reuiuing of this our new <hi>Spa's</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, whoſe vertue (I am perſwaded) will be found ſo farre to tranſeend, that the natiue Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the <hi>Spa,</hi> will ſoone finde this our diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery to draw from them no ſmall commodity;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1083:15"/> for that this once diuulged, will be a meanes not onely to enduce thoſe of our owne Countrey to forbeare their recourſe thither, but is like to proue very effectuall to inuite many ſtrangers to vs, who with more ſafety may reape the benefit of this our water, than the diſtracted, and diſioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted affaires of <hi>Germany</hi> will ſuffer.</p>
            <p>And why ſhould any doubt that this water of ours ſhould not as amply and effectually worke in the cure of infirmities that are of an obſtructiue nature, as the <hi>Spa?</hi> That it hath a moſt apparant ſenſible <hi>Spa</hi> taſte, I dare (beſides my own experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) referre it to the iudgement of any, whoſe pallate hath not loſt, the remembrance of that water. That vitrioll hath the predominancy in it, beſides the taſte, infallible concluſion hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. That it worketh in the ſame manner with the <hi>Spa,</hi> hath alſo been ſatisfactorily tried. If any one reply, that they deny not but that this our ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed <hi>Iewel</hi> may haue a litle alliance with the <hi>Spa,</hi> but it muſt needs be in a poore degree, for that the place is naked of Mineralls, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared with the <hi>Spa,</hi> whoſe territorie doth ſo abound with them, that extraordinary commodity is drawne daily from the ſubſtantiall Mines themſelues: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, firſt it will not be denied but that this our water doth paſſe by Minerall veines, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1083:16"/> it to retaine a taſte which differs it from other waters: which being granted, I demand who is ſo wiſe, or rather foole-hardy, as to dare to propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the quantity of ſo hidden a myſtery, which Nature hath ſecreted to her ſelfe as a priuacy (like many others) inſcrutable? How came our inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtible Mynes of Iron, Lead, Copper, Allum, and why ſhould I not name Coale, which not onely furniſh vs, but with their ſurpluſage, are tranſported to other Kingdomes, with no ſmall gaine, to be firſt knowne? Were they reuealed in a dreame, like S. <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> head, or rather skull, which was made knowne (as it is fabled or Legended) to a deuout Monke in his ſleepe, and is to be ſeene at <hi>Amiens?</hi> No ſure, induſtry and paines (the price which the Heathens could ſay the Gods did ſet vpon whatſoeuer is excellent) firſt gaue them light and life. The ſame induſtry (there is no doubt) would alſo make knowne to vs many new treaſures, which is onely wanting, and not matter. To make this good in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular in hand.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spa</hi> (I know) doth boaſt of her Mineralls of Iron, Vitrioll, Sulphur, &amp; others, of whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties they haue ſeuerall waters that doe taſte, &amp; operate. You may remember I gaue a touch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that beſides this our new <hi>Spa,</hi> wee tooke a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1083:16"/> view of other Springs of differing natures, of which I will briefly relate, whereby it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that (vnleſſe we will beleeue nothing but what we ſee) we are not vnfurniſhed of ſeuerall ſorts of Mineralls (how ſecretly ſoeuer yet hid from vs) and that within the circle of the Moore, where the <hi>Tuit-well</hi> is ſeated, and the bordering places thereabout.</p>
            <p>In our firſt daies view of the <hi>Tuit-well,</hi> we were conducted by our guide a mile and more beyond it, to looke vpon another water, which he with much adoe found, for that it is very obſcurely placed. It breakes forth in the skirt of an hill, cloſe by a Riuolet. We were no ſooner come neere it, but we were (vnmannerly) taken by the noſe with a moſt vnſufferable Sulphurie fume, at the firſt not eaſie to be endured. The firſt thing we did, was to giue the water a more free paſſage than we found it had; which done, we tooke of it into a glaſſe to view. It was tranſparently cleare, but of ſo ſtrong and intolerable a ſent, being held neere, that a more ſuffocating ſmell could hardly be deuiſed. Both by the taſte and ſent it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, that it is of a ſulphurous nature, and that in a high degree, but withal exceeding brackiſh &amp; ſalt. The day wayning would not giue vs leaue to ſtay long in the place: for concluſion-ſake
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1083:17"/> onely, we put an eye-cup of ſiluer into a glaſſe of the water, which within a little ſpace turned it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Copper tincture.</p>
            <p>The next day (being our ſecond of viſiting the <hi>Tuit-well</hi>) we were drawne aſide into <hi>Bilton</hi> Parke, which bordereth vpon the Moore, where in the declination of an hill, we came to a Spring, much of the ſame condition with the former, the ſmell as violent, and the taſte the ſame, ſaue that it is not perceiueably ſalt. An vnder-keeper of the Parke, whom we asked what vſe was made of the water, told vs, that not long before, finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe all out of tune, ſo that no ordinary labour, nor abſtinency could ſet him right: he made bold to drinke of this water a glaſſe, or two. It purged him (not without violence) both waies, driuing forth of his body much venimous matter, which after by waſhing in it dryed vp and healed. Hee ſhewed vs alſo a poore man-ſeruant to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who being for the ſpace of two yeares trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a grieuous paine in one of his legs, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a numneſſe and ſwelling, being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed to waſh in this water, was within an vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected time reſtored to health, and ſtrength, and hath continued firme and ſound euer ſince.</p>
            <p>From hence we were brought to another wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, diſtant from this place about a mile, called
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1083:17"/> 
               <hi>Pigeon</hi> Spring, of the continuall haunt they haue about it. This is alſo of a Sulphury quality, and ſalt, but in a more remiſſe and moderate degree than either of the other.</p>
            <p>It were a great daring in me (who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my ſelfe ignorant in the leaſt rudiments of Art) to affirme any thing peremptorily of the true nature of theſe ſulphurous Springs, their proper vſe, or what intermixture they may haue of ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Mineralls. Nay, it were a touch of boldneſſe in any (be they who they will) poſitiuely to ſet downe the certaine effects of theſe waters, becauſe (the three laſt named hauing apparant differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) their faculties haue not by any (that I can heare) beene ſeriouſly tried and examined. Yet that by probability (ſeeing they are ſulphurous, and that in a high degree) they are vſefull, none (who will not abſolutely deny the vertues of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls) will deny. Why they are ſo exceeding ſtrong of ſent, and taſte, and yet not hot, as are the waters of the Bath in <hi>Summerſet-ſhire,</hi> parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king both of the ſame coniectured nature, I leaue to the diſcuſſing of Chimiſts and Mineralliſts. Some vndertake to affirme, that the Minerall matter which feeds the waters of the Bath, and makes them operatiue, is fiered. Theſe affirme, (grounding themſelues vpon <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) that there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1083:18"/> are certaine hot and dry exhalations included in the cauernes of the earth, which ſeeking paſſage forth, and vent, and not finding any, they are vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently carried vp and downe, in which motion by degrees they ratifie, and at length are fired. If ſo it happen (ſay they) that where ſuch vapours are included, and incendiated, there be any By tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous or Sulphurous matter, by this meanes it comes to be fired: and looke how long there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains any of the Minerall to feed the fire, ſo long the fire laſteth. And ſince (ſay they) theſe Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls haue a perpetuall regeneration, it muſt needs follow, that the fire fed by them muſt alſo be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, vnleſſe it finde paſſage forth, &amp; ſo vaniſh. If this heate thus encloſed in theſe hollows be great and intenſe, the matter of the Minerall plentifull, and that the water which paſſeth by them in a continuall ſucceſſion makes no long courſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it breake forth, then is the water in its iſſue ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hot. But if the heate be ſmall (whereunto the abundance of matter giueth force, as we ſee in our common experience of our ordinary fewell) and the paſſage of the water long before it iſſue, then commeth it to paſſe, that the water is either of a moderate warmth, or cold; for that in ſo long a iourney it paſſeth by ſtones, and cold places, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by degrees the heate it receiued.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:1083:18"/>
            <p>For my part, I am more apt to admire Nature in the rarity and variety of her producements, than willing to trouble my braine in ſearching into things (it may be) not knowable. If ſuch as are iudicious would take the paines by any artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall coutſe, to examine the difference of theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ours, and thoſe of the Bath, <hi>ſecundùm magis &amp; minus,</hi> whereby their due vſe might be known, it were a labour which might merit applauſe. We make no bones to expend great ſummes in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes of momentary continuance, and ſuffer our eares to be inculcated with rare and vſefull won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derments of Nature, and paſſe them by as matters belonging onely to Mechanicke knowledge; whereas (truely weighed) theſe high myſteries would better become both our charge &amp; ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And whoſoeuer they are, whoſe ouerflow of fortunes doth inuite them to leaue to poſterity an allowance (whereby they worthily expreſſe a laudable &amp; Chriſtian aime at the common good) be it in erecting Schooles, Hoſpitals, or what elſe ſoeuer of that kind; if ſuch would pleaſe to weigh the benefit of theſe waters, they could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deuiſe (their vſe being firſt aſſuredly knowne, and experimented) any meanes more apt to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deare themſelues to their Countrey, than in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing a largeſſe, in fitting ſuch places as theſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1083:19"/> (where medicinall waters by the goodneſſe of God are offered vnto vs) for their commodious vſe. For, although the greateſt Subiects of this Land may be forced to craue the aide of theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (for where Art is at a <hi>non-plus,</hi> Nature often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſupplieth) yet it is the poorer ſort, to whom they are like to yeeld the greateſt reliefe, many of whom often periſh for want of outward meanes. How many diſtreſſed ſoules lie languiſhing in fearefull infirmities, whom the Northerne parts doe diſtance ſo farre from the Bathes in <hi>Summer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-ſhire,</hi> that they ſink vnder the burthen of their diſeaſe, either through debility of body to make ſo long a iourney? Or, if their bodies would giue them leaue, the weight of their pouerty preſſeth them downe, and keepes them backe: whereas a reaſonable charge beſtowed on theſe our waters (which are yet but like Beare-whelpes, and want the licking of Art to giue them vſefull forme) might proue as memorable an act as moſt are in theſe times. I know the Bathes in <hi>Summerſet-ſhire</hi> (which I once ſaw) haue in a reaſonable propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (being happily ſeated in a place which draws from the recourſe of ſtrangers no ſmall commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity) beene look't into, and indifferently accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated: Yet compare them with others of the like kinde beyond the Seas (which I haue heard
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1083:19"/> by authentique report to be excellently ordered) they are but poore and of meane value. Thoſe of <hi>Akan, Aix,</hi> or <hi>Aquiſgrane</hi> (call the place which you will, for they are all one) I haue ſeen, being about 15. miles from the <hi>Spa,</hi> and beheld them with great admiration; the ſtructure about them being ſo commodious, that they may be tempered at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure according to the habit of the patient. They may alſo be let forth in an inſtant, (and euery day that they are vſed they are) by which meanes they are freed from the ordure and filth which they attract from putride bodies, which (no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) might preiudice thoſe of ſound temper. There are ſome kept priuate for women, where vnſeene they may (without the leaſt preiudice to their modeſty) enter for their benefit. This is far from our (I may well ſay heatheniſh) cuſtome, where men and women doe mutually entermixe in the Bath, whereby there is too great an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on adminiſtred of begetting luſtfull fires, cauſing the ſoules of many to run a doubtfull hazard. But I leaue this diſorder to the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe, whoſe authority is able to rectifie this groſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, and returne to our waters.</p>
            <p>Oppoſition (I know) they ſhall not want (Worth &amp; Enuy being inſeparable companions) for there are ſome ſo betroth't to their particular,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1083:20"/> and ſo ingulft in auarice, that they haue vowed neuer to know any other loue. Theſe, if they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the leaſt dram of profit, to be drawne from their profeſſion (I ſpeake of ſuch whoſe liueli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood conſiſts in phyſicall directions, or manuall cures) by any extraordinary diſcouery, let it neuer ſo apparantly benefit the generall, they rack their braines to inuent any meanes of diſparaging it, and bedlem-like raile at whatſoever may bring diminution to their profit and practiſe, their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate gaine being dearer to them than their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, nay than the whole world. But let the galls of ſuch greaten, till ſweld with enuy, they burſt; the teſtimony of one approued man will be of ſufficient weight to out-ballance the fuming froth of a thouſand ſuch.</p>
            <p>It did not coſt vs aboue one entire day in this our perambulation of viſiting theſe waters, but by what we had ſeene, we thought it more than coniecturable, that vpon diligent ſearch there may many others be found within a ſmall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ſeuerall intermixed natures, which may afford admirable vſe both for outward &amp; inward cure, diſpenced by the appointment of a carefull and iudicious Artiſt.</p>
            <p>Can we then be ſo ſimple as to queſtion, where there are ſuch variety of Minerall waters, whether
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1083:20"/> the ſoile doth afford commodious veines, or no? I am perſwaded, if thoſe ſame <hi>Belgicke</hi> Piſmires (as one not vnfitly calls them) were maſters of ſo faire an oportunity as this doth promiſe, they would leaue no angle of the place vnſought, till they had found out the beds where theſe Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls ſleepe. But we (like Carriers horſes) will not out of the tract way of ordinary commodities. Peace the mother of plenty, and this the nurſe of caſe, or rather idleneſſe, hath ſo enthralled vs, that we hug our ſelues in our owne ſecurity, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect many bleſſings which the liberall hand of the Almighty hath ſhowred vpon vs.</p>
            <p>O that their example (I meane the <hi>Hollanders</hi>) might moue vs to conſider, what bleſſings doe attend a laborious life. How haue they (confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within a bog (as I may ſay) and that of no great compaſſe) aduanced their heads aboue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny States, that poſſeſſe large &amp; fertile Dominions? What Cities of magnifique ſtructure doe they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit? How doe they abound in all manner of profitable Manifactures? Into what place of the habitable world haue the not trafficke? How haue they bearded that ſame Chriſtendome-threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-Monarch the Catholique King, and done him more ſhame (maugre all his Indian Bullion) than all his farre-fetcht conqueſts haue gained
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1083:21"/> him credit? And whence comes this their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, and encreaſe of potency, if not from a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall circumſpection, &amp; ſagacity in their affaires, cheriſhing all manner of vſefull Arts, and aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious knowledge, and not ſuffering any vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable weeds, I meane idle perſons, to harbour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them? Whereas we (by what conniuence I know not) giue way to more loytering droanes, and common able beggars, to ſwarme in our ſtreets, than would ſerue to people a larger circuit of ground than they poſſeſſe.</p>
            <p>Whence is it that our Alehouſes and Tauernes are in ſuch requeſt in all good Townes, but that they are ſo frequented with idle companions that their cuſtome is thought now adaies a conſtant faire reuenue? And hence it is that moſt of our Townes-maſters (obſeruing the humor and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of the times) howſoeuer they make a ſhew of ſome bundles of Flax, a few bars of Iron, or ſuch like ſtuffe in their ſhops, yet (the plaine Engliſh is) Corne is the maine prop of their eſtates, &amp; of Corne, Barley, which they know will off, when all other commodities ſticke faſt. Thus come Tipling-houſes to be in ſuch requeſt, &amp; ſo coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced in their exceſſe of riot, and abuſe of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, thoſe who are appointed Gouernouts (but may more properly be tearmed Ouerſeers) winc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1083:21"/> at diſorder, becauſe (like Flies) they deriue a great part of their Being from the corruptions &amp; ſores of the times. Indeed we doe but too much abound in all neceſſary comforts, and this is it which hath ſo infected vs with a lazie Lethargy, that through a long habit of eaſe, we are growne vncapable of ſuſtaining any paines. Hath not our long continued peace, brought vs to a ſtrange paſſe (being neither employed at home in fit la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, nor ſuffered to paſſe abroad but with ſtrange reſtrictions, and limitations) when wee are become the proſtitutes of forraigne deriſion? Tis how the golden Age was, when wee were held a terrour to the proudeſt of our neighbours, our alliance was ſought vnto as a ſhelter, and they were ſafeſt, whom the wings of our amity did ſhadow: but we are now ſo ferre from being remembred with the leaſt phraſe of reſpect, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our preſent ſtupidity, and baſe ſufferings, that a beggarly baſe fiſher-Towne (fit to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what it is, a <hi>Cacus</hi> his den, and recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of pilfering Pyrats) dares braue vs at our own doores, ſo that not a Merchant but feares to put forth his head, to paſſe from one of our Ports to another. We are daily defied vpon the skirts of our owne coaſts, ſo that not a weeke doth paſſe, which bringeth not forth ſome ſad tydings, euen
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1083:22"/> in our view, to the vndoing or hazarding of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a poore family. O the benummed temper of theſe our daies, when we who were the great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of theſe our Seas, are now growne ſuch for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dide ſlaues, that we are ſcornfully trampled vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and beaten at our owne weapon! We ſit by our fires ſide, wiſh all were well, ſcatter now and then a few words of feare, as if our hearts did miſ-giue all were not well, but that ſome terror were at hand; and yet none ſo bold, of ſo Roman a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, or ſo louing to his Countrey, as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime our hazard, or giue warning of a ſtorme; which whenſoeuer it ſhall breake forth, (which God auert, and yet conſidering our too well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen weakneſſe, and ſupine careleſneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the deluges of many crying ſinnes, it may be feared it is not farre off) we ſhall be found but an amazed ſort of ſtaggering ſlumberers, ſcarce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake. Yet I hope in this our <hi>Iſrael</hi> (I was about to haue ſaid <hi>Sodome,</hi> for in fulneſſe of bread, if not in other her abominations, we may be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to haue too great a ſhare) there will be found ſome faithfull <hi>Abrahams,</hi> who will make bold to ſpeake vnto the Lord againe, and againe, that he will not deſtroy the righteous with the wicked. We haue lately ſmarted vnder the hand of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty by a grieuous viſitation, and we ſee (bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1083:22"/> be his name) he hath cauſed his Angell to s;tay his hand, ſo that there is mercy with our God, O that we had grace to feare him! If this will not warne vs, but that we will ſtill go on in a careleſſe courſe, we cannot but expect (which he who was according to Gods owne heart, did tremble to make choice on) to fall into the hands of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, whoſe ſwords haue long thirſted after our bloud. Yet ſince (moſt mighty Lord God) thy prouidence hath hitherto miraculouſly wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ouer vs: O (howſoeuer our ſinnes do moſt iuſtly prouoke thee to hide thy face from vs) bee not farre off (thou preſeruer of man) when wee call vpon thee. Euer preſerue, and graciouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our dread Soueraigne. Keepe farre from him ſuch as were the young Counſellors of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam;</hi> when they would whiſper into his ſacred eares the encreaſe of our burthens, or the doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our taxes, let their tongues cleaue vnto the roofe of their mouthes. Let thoſe be deare vnto him, who ſincerely tender the glory of thy great Name, that ſo Religion may firſt in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations be aduanced and eſtabliſhed, Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Matchiauellia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s may be extirpated, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good by a carefull prouiding for our ſafery at home, before we embroile our ſelues abroad, may be ſecured: that other Nations, ſeeing our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1083:23"/> proſperity, may be forced to ſay of vs, <hi>Bleſſed are the people who are in ſuch a caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The iſſue of this long digreſſion (beſides that a ſudden apprehenſion of our threatning hazard, by the tollerated multiplying of Romiſh Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts, and the extreame weakneſſe of our coaſts did tranſport me) is only to ſhew, that if we were ſo cautelous as befits vs, and ſo ſolicitous as we ſhould be, of the publike good, this our happy Ile, doth afford matter ſufficient of vſefull conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, partly by a free &amp; equall trade abroad, &amp; partly by exerciſe at home, to employ all the ruſty hands, and idle mouldy braines amongſt vs; which till it be with more care aduiſed on (than it hath beene long, but eſpecially of late) let vs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer expect to returne to our priſtine farre-ſpred glory.</p>
            <p>It was pitty this our new <hi>Spa</hi> did not firſt fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of ſome of our iugling impoſturing, Romiſh Prieſts: for if they (by their Mountebank trickes) are able to draw from moſt parts of the Kingdome, to one of their Sainted Wells, a world of people, ſome whereof they cure meerely with conceit of their waters ſoueraignty; others (ayling little or nothing) they can perſwade to publiſh of themſelues ſtupendious cures, of deſperate diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (which being for the aduancement of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1083:23"/> cauſe (though in it ſelfe a baſe lie) yet with them is but a veniall <hi>peccadelio</hi>) if I ſay theſe bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen fac't Empericks, are able to goe ſo farre with an ordinary plaine water, what a ſhame is it for vs who haue ſuch a reall, vertuall Spring, nay many, and that within a ſmall diſtance, thus to be out-ſtript with their legerdemaine?</p>
            <p>In the latter end of this Summer there was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Spring diſcouered by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Leake,</hi> a Phyſitian of <hi>Yorke,</hi> a mile neerer the Towne of <hi>Knares<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> than is the <hi>Tuit-well.</hi> It is held to be as good as the other, of the ſame taſte, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of the ſame facultie. So that now we may boldly challenge the <hi>Spa</hi> in <hi>Germany:</hi> for as they haue their two acide Fountaines, <hi>Sauenir,</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hon,</hi> we equall them, and want nothing but names to giue ours the greater ſound.</p>
            <p>But it is time to ſtrike ſaile. I might (and not vnaptly) take occaſion, before I conclude, to publiſh many rarities which the Towne of <hi>Knaresbrough,</hi> and the bordering places doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, as the variety of ſtone Quarries, the ſeuerall ſorts of Earths, rare Plants, and other moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruable ſpecialties. Here alſo might I not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently inſiſt a little of the famous chronicled dropping Well, ſeated vnder the Towne, which turneth whatſoeuer is caſt into it, or caſually falls
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1083:24"/> in, as ſtickes, leaues, and moſſe, into a firme ſtone; which ſhewes it to be of a moſt aſtrictiue quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and of appliable vſe. A proofe hereof was made the precedent Summer by a ſtranger, who caſually paſſing this way (hauing been long trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a flix) was counſelled to drinke of this water, which (other meanes failing) he willingly did, and within a few daies was perfectly cured of the diſeaſe. That theſe Fountains alſo arc con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently ſeated neere a Towne of ample receipt for ſtrangers, is not to be omitted. Yet theſe and many other remarkable aduantages I am content to ſlip ouer, hoping ſome generous ſpirit will vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake their more ample diſcouery, which would be an act well-becomming any one, who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to perpetuate his name in the Catalogue of ſuch as haue giuen luſter to their Countrey. By this meanes the wonderments of this place ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly related, and divulged, we may haue iuſt cauſe to glorifie God, who amongſt other his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numbered fauours, both concerning our ſoules, and bodies, hath added the knowledge of theſe waters, and his vndeſerued mercies conſidered, we may truly confeſſe, <hi>He hath not dealt ſo with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1083:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
